<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Eduardo Donoso</title>
    <description>Travel writer + outdoor enthusiast</description>
    <link>https://edonoso.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://edonoso.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 14:37:13 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 14:37:13 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Finding My Place in the NYC Community with Greenmarket</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Carrots, radishes, and beets are here. Moments later, apples arrive across the square along the pears. Bread and honey take over the center, while the herbs and plants announce their arrival with their characteristic scents. The farmers finish their last details and we are set to start a new day at one of the 50 farmers markets in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I was sailing in the Patagonian fjords patrolling the Chilean sea, and now I’m worrying about the late frost that killed blooming fruits upstate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 10 years, I worked in the Chilean Navy as part of the Coast Guard. Growing weary of the ocean, and admittedly too seasick, I left my job to seek new opportunities. When I arrived in New York City, I immersed myself in my newly adopted community. I missed connecting with diverse groups like locals, scientists, seamen, and fishermen in my Navy days. Becoming a volunteer at the Greenmarket Program for GrowNYC was the perfect solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;The more knowledge people have about the way their food is produced, the more likely it is that their values – and not just “value” – will inform their purchasing decisions.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;-Michael Pollan, &lt;a href=&quot;http://michaelpollan.com/articles-archive/no-bar-code/&quot; title=&quot;No bar code&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;No bar code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my first day as a volunteer, I got a taste for what it takes to organize a farmers market. I saw many vendors selling all sorts of products; big trucks parked in the open space; and of course all the customers shopping at the market. This market wasn’t any different from what I saw in the ferias of my home country, but within the first few minutes of my training, my Market Manager explained to me the things I didn’t see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/sunrise-market.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Preparing for a new day at the farmers market&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Preparing for a new day at the farmers market&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the vendors sell only local, seasonal, and fresh products, and they drive in from no more than 3 hours away. “So the apple vendor is a farmer?” I asked her and before I knew it, that same farmer gave me a free class on the life cycle of the apples they picked the day before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything I heard that day was so new to me. I really didn’t know this before, and honestly, hadn’t thought too much about talking with these vendors nor asking them about the origin of my food. But I realized in that moment how much I could learn from these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More surprises were waiting for me that day when I realized I would be in charge of the popular cooking demonstrations at the market. The idea is simple. Check what ingredients are available that day at your market, choose your recipe, and prepare it for your customers. Well, I had never cooked for more than myself when I was in the Chilean Navy. I was nervous about the challenge, but soon it became second nature—chopping and cooking vegetables, while navigating the questions of our curious customers. “Oh, what are you making today?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/cooking-demo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The famous cooking demos&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The famous cooking demos&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greenmarket’s mission is to promote regional agriculture and ensure that all New Yorkers have access to fresh and locally grown food, including low income communities. The local farmers market is one of the biggest contributors to that goal considering the everyday impact the markets have on their communities. As a native Spanish speaker, I was happy to make accessible this same information to the Spanish speaking communities of NYC as well. The happy faces of neighbors when they see their square, park, street or sidewalk transform into a unique gathering place between them and their local farmers is very rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been two years since I became a Market Manager at Greenmarket. The beginning was challenging. I still remember my first day at the 175th St. Greenmarket (uptown Manhattan). This market is one of the oldest (over 30 years old!) and is located right in the heart of Washington Heights. Just as my first day started, I was exposed to all the situations that are never supposed to happen. Calling 911 for a customer that had fainted; a filming shoot, parking proceedings by NYPD to name a few. At least the floor wasn’t moving like when I was at sea! But, I was not alone. Behind every Market Manager is a family of four Regional Coordinators, friendly staff, and volunteers ready to help and support you. Also, the majority of the team started just like you as a volunteer or Market Manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every farmers market is unique because it is immersed in a community with a distinct identity. The biggest challenge is connecting that community with their local farmers, and it is right there where the Market Manager plays a key role. We help coordinate fun activities and information sessions like drawings, face painting, infographics, pictures, costumes, recipes, cooking demonstrations, contests, holiday celebrations, tours for kids and adults, and outreach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/edu-choclo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;One of the healthiest costumes for Halloween&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One of the healthiest costumes for Halloween&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/edu-poster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It&apos;s class time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It&apos;s class time&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/edu-teaching.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Explaining to the community about GrowNYC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Explaining to the community about GrowNYC&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/edu-dias-nacionales.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Celebrating Chilean National Day&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Celebrating Chilean National Day&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/queens-market.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Corona Farmers Market in Queens&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Corona Farmers Market in Queens&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/happy-farmers-market.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dag Hammarskjold Plaza Farmers Market in Manhattan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Dag Hammarskjold Plaza Farmers Market in Manhattan&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the most important part of the market is undoubtedly the farmers. Greenmarket ensures that new Market Managers learn about the day-to-day of our farmers; during training week, we spend one day visiting and working in a farm upstate. Before, I never really questioned the process of how my food arrived at my plate and the importance of the people that participate in it. Now I’m constantly reminded of the important work of farmers, and understand much better the livelihood of some of my relatives living in the Chilean countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned a lot during the last two seasons working at the Greenmarket. Every conversation with the farmers, the community, the team, and the members of other programs at GrowNYC (recycling, gardening, and education) has inspired my new approach in life. I’ve incorporated what I’ve learned into my daily routines and my home. I built my first garden in my backyard. I added some new recipes to my repertoire. I finished my first worm compost bin, and made compost from the food scraps from my kitchen. Now whenever I travel to a new place, my trip wouldn’t be complete without visiting at least one local farmer’s market or farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the end of the day here at the 175th St. Greenmarket. The farmers are loading up their trucks and are waiting for my signal to turn out the square. I wait for everybody to leave and look at the now empty space. Tomorrow another community will wake up to the colors and scents that local and fresh food provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nyc-greenmarket/greenmarket-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Farmers Market on 175th with Broadway in Manhattan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Farmers Market on 175th with Broadway in Manhattan&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 08:55:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://edonoso.com/NYC-Greenmarket/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://edonoso.com/NYC-Greenmarket/</guid>
        
        <category>sustainability</category>
        
        <category>local</category>
        
        <category>new-york</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Postholing at Mont du Lac des Cygnes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Running in one of the oldest mountain ranges on earth, adding a new word ‘postholing’ to our vocabulary and making the best of a foggy day at Mont du Lac des Cygnes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All throughout the car ride, we couldn’t see anything - a thick fog was continually asking us if we want to keep going or return to the city. Having traveled so far we decided to keep postponing the decision…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then we made it - the Mont du Lac des Cygnes Visitor Center - empty and with the same thick fog and foreboding feeling for what was to come. We had no clue where was the summit, but the snow in the trail was firm making a crunchy sound as we ran. Why should we insist on going to the summit, knowing we won’t have a view? And why are the trail markers so close to the ground? We were about to find the answers in the toughest way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Forget CrossFit. Forget hot yoga, Soulcycle, Soloflex, and your Body Pump class. There is no better short-duration, full-body workout than postholing.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;–Maren Horjus, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.backpacker.com/skills/winter-skills-snowshoeing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The case for postholing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trail running or snow running, in this case, was more difficult that we thought. The crunchy sound of the snow changed to a grumbling sound after our feet were swallowed by the snow as we stepped slightly off the tiny path. We plunged hip deep in the snow around 30 times. We had no idea there was a word for this - ‘postholing’. (A great description for this word &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtco.com/what-is-postholing-1766135&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question was - how high are we running over the real path? Well, you can find a clue in this picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/postholing-mont-lac-cygnes/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Postholing&quot; title=&quot;Postholing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Postholing&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/postholing-mont-lac-cygnes/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finding the trail marker&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Finding the trail marker&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/postholing-mont-lac-cygnes/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View at the top&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;View at the top&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/postholing-mont-lac-cygnes/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1 billion years ago&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;1 billion years ago&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/postholing-mont-lac-cygnes/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mont du Lac des Cygnes in the left side&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Mont du Lac des Cygnes in the left side&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/postholing-mont-lac-cygnes/7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Time to enjoy the view in the parking lot, behind us Mont du Lac à Moïse&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Time to enjoy the view in the parking lot, behind us Mont du Lac à Moïse&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we seriously running over 1 meter above the real path, being swallowed by the snow every step and still thinking we are going make it to the summit? …  The answer was a resounding YES.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We followed a wooden boardwalk near the summit with some flat rocky surfaces as well. We arrived at the top of Mont du Lac des Cygnes, with a nice and incredible… thick fog that allowed us to see nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not wanting to give up, we waited 30 minutes at the chilly summit, hoping the strong wind would blow the fog away.  In the meantime, one of the information posts on the summit caught our attention. Mont du Lac des Cygnes, part of the Laurentian Mountains, is only 980 meters high and formed 1 billion years ago (For perspective Mount Everest and Mount Blanc are only 200 million years old). After a little more digging we found that the Laurentian Mountains in Canada, are number 10 in the list of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buzzfeed.com/top10s/oldest-mountains-on-earth-ww6q?utm_term=.ic4kJlRrG#.elPgPJBkq&quot;&gt;the oldest mountains on earth&lt;/a&gt;. What an amazing experience to be able to walk over one of the oldest mountains in the world. Unfortunately, we weren’t able to enjoy the view of the Laurentian range from here but maybe in the summer time, we can try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After little change in cloud cover at the summit, we decided it was time to go back down the mountain. We half ran, half potholed down the trail. When we arrived at the parking area, suddenly to our surprise, a clear, sunny and warm day took over the fog and the cold. In front of us, we could see old Mont du Lac des Cygnes. We knew this would happen, and we enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good to Know:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can get a really nice map of Parc National Des Grands-Jardins &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sepaq.com/dotAsset/840e9681-d144-4736-b81a-61b42cceb963.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information for others activities in the park are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sepaq.com/pq/grj/index.dot?language_id=1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The length of the trail is 8.78 km round trip. You can add more kilometers if you take the long loop to return to the parking area.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The price for visiting the park is $8 per person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 13:31:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://edonoso.com/postholing-mont-lac-cygnes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://edonoso.com/postholing-mont-lac-cygnes/</guid>
        
        <category>travels</category>
        
        <category>canada</category>
        
        <category>quebec</category>
        
        <category>trail-running</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Canoe Camping in La Mauricie National Park in Québec, Canada</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;2 kilometers of portage, beautiful lakes, calm water, solitude with amazing sunrises and sunsets, do you want to hear more? Come on board Canoe-Camping at La Mauricie National Park, Quebec.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An incredible first adventure mixing our knowledge of camping with our new activity, canoeing. Without a doubt, we made a lot of mistakes that we want to share with you as well as good stories. Getting the best of La Mauricie Canoe Camping. First advice - bring mosquito repellent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to jump in the water! I can’t resist anymore! It’s raining, and aren’t mosquitos supposed to disappear when it’s raining?! I am pretty sure that everybody has suffered bad situations during adventures that now are only memories that you can laugh about with your friends. Well, this is one of this stories, especially now while I am writing and watching the videos about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;La Mauricie is commonly cited as one of the best places in the country to see stunning foliage, especially in the fall.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Celina Torrijos, &lt;a href=&quot;http://farandwide.much.com/la-mauricie-camping-trip/&quot; title=&quot;Far&amp;amp;Wide&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Far&amp;amp;Wide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A one week trip to Quebec, it was time to use our National Park Discovery Pass. We chose La Mauricie National Park for their backcountry camping and to fulfill that dream in mind of paddling to our campsite with the view of the sunset. Sounds good or no?
The campsite was on Lac Dauphinais, if you see it on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pc.gc.ca/en/pn-np/qc/mauricie/visit/cartes-maps&quot; title=&quot;Parks Canada map&quot;&gt;Parks Canada map&lt;/a&gt; there is no road to get there so paddling/portaging was the way to go. It includes the following path:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;500 meter portage from parking to Lac Soumire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paddling Lac Soumire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;500 meter portage from Lac Soumire to Lac Giron&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paddling Lac Giron&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 km from Lac Giron to Lac Dauphinais&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paddling from the south side of Lac Dauphinais to our campsite, in this case #2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the portage itself wasn’t that bad (no regrets in the moment about getting the lighter canoe!), in our second portage is when the mosquitos started. Almost arriving at Lac Dauphinais we were attacked by a cloud of mosquitos, our only relief was when we arrived at the center of the lake and a breeze moved them away. Now we see why all the other paddlers we saw were covered head to toe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At our campsite, we found two designated areas separately with a toilet in between. At this point we changed to more layers to protect our skin. Anyway these little guys found a way to bite us between our fingers while we were preparing our dinner. The mosquito situation was at that point very unpleasant. The only way to be safe was inside of the tent, since making a fire wasn’t allowed at this particular campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/la-mauricie-canoe-camping/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view from the campsite on Lac Dauphinais&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The view from the campsite on Lac Dauphinais&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/la-mauricie-canoe-camping/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Getting water from Lac Dauphinais&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Getting water from Lac Dauphinais&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/la-mauricie-canoe-camping/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Another portage complete in La Mauricie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Another portage complete in La Mauricie&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/la-mauricie-canoe-camping/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rain and mosquitos in La Mauricie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Rain and mosquitos followed us for our entire trip in La Mauricie&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/la-mauricie-canoe-camping/7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Final portage to the parking area from Lac Soumire&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Final portage to the parking area from Lac Soumire&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/la-mauricie-canoe-camping/8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mosquitos in La Mauricie National Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We laugh about this now&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early morning we decided we had had enough, the sunrise was  beginning and we took that opportunity to pack up camp. Again the mosquito situation wasn’t the best so we decided to get off shore and prepare coffee on board. The coffee turned out to be one of the best ever, maybe it got a special taste from all the effort we put in trying not to capsize while preparing it on the canoe. The solitude of being the only ones on the lake was amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our energy boost ready we continue our trip when it started drizzling. We were happy because rain means no mosquitos. We were so wrong - we got more bites during our paddle and then twice as much during our portages. Legs swollen and red, we arrived at our car and finished this first adventure at La Mauricie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things to keep it in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure you &lt;a href=&quot;https://reservation.pc.gc.ca/LaMauricieNationalParkofCanada/LaMauricieBackcountry?Map&amp;amp;gccf=true&quot; title=&quot;Parks Canada Reservation System&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;make a reservation&lt;/a&gt; for canoe camping ahead of time. Upon your arrival to the park, stop by the park office for your permit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you see the pictures we didn’t cover our legs because we thought insect repellent was enough, but it wasn’t. Now I see why everybody was wearing long pants.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be careful taking a dip on the coast of the Lac Dauphinais since there are leeches. We only explore the area around campsite #2 so don’t know if they are elsewhere as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The trails for portaging are very well marked, easy to follow, and relatively flat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The only source of water by our campsite was from lake. We paddled to the center of the lake to get water because it was pretty swampy by the shore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://edonoso.com/la-mauricie-canoe-camping/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://edonoso.com/la-mauricie-canoe-camping/</guid>
        
        <category>travels</category>
        
        <category>quebec</category>
        
        <category>canada</category>
        
        <category>canoe</category>
        
        <category>camping</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
